Guide to the Jeanmarie Amend collection, 1977-1982 UA 410
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Jeanmarie Amend Collection
1977-1982
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Gladu, John (Grungy)
UA 410
2 Linear Feet 4 boxes
The Jeanmarie Amend collection is a snapshot of the life of a student at Rice in the early 1980s. A prolific writer (both professionally and personally), Jeanmarie recorded several journals detailing her time at Rice. In addition to her school papers, the collection contains schoolbooks, news clippings, correspondence, photographs, and memorabilia--each contributing the the vibrant picture of Jeanmarie's university days.
Biographical / Historical
Jeanmarie Amend attended Rice University from 1979 to 1982. She majored in English, wrote for the Thresher and was member of Jones college. The collection contains notes, essays, and exams from several of the classes Jeanmarie was taking her senior year, including Shakespeare, American Poetry, French, and Medical Ethics--as well as samples of her writing throughout high school and college
Jeanmarie had two younger siblings--Charlotte and Matthew. After college, Jeanmarie considered a number of options, including graduate school at the University of Houston, teaching abroad, opening her own food bank to assist homeless children and young adults, and working as a public affairs writer in the private sector.
Scope and Contents
The Jeanmarie Amend collection is made up of school papers (including notes, essays, exams, and books), news clippings and notes concerning post-graduation options, personal papers such as journals, correspondence, and photographs, and memorabilia including dress patterns, boxes, and a small sewing kit. The materials are in good condition and range in date from 1977 to 1982. Researchers interested in the lives of students at Rice, or the emergence of women into educational and professional fields in the early 1980s would find this collection insightful.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The materials were donated by John (Grungy) Gladu in May of 2019.
Separated Materials
Books removed from collection: "A Midsummer Night's Dream" by Shakespeare, "poems" by Wallace Stevens, "Poems and prose by Gerard Manley Hopkins" Selected and Edited by W. H. Gardner, "The Burning Mystery of Anna in 1951" by Kenneth Koch, "Sound and Sense: An Introduction to Poetry, 3rd Ed." by Laurence Perrine, and "Contemporary American Poetry, 3rd ed." by A. Poulin, Jr.
Index Terms
Subjects
Maps; Newspapers--Sections, columns, etc.; Universities and colleges
Document Types
books; photographs; black-and-white photographs; diaries; essays; personal correspondence; programs (documents); lecture notes; memorabilia
Subjects (Persons)
Gladu, John (Grungy)
- Series I: Personal Papers
  - Sub-Series A: Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - To Geoff [from Jeanmarie], 1978-06-02
    - M. T. Cuervo, 1980-11-18
    - To Maria Teresa [from Jeanmarie], 1981-01-21
    - Marie Teresa Cuervo, 1981-07-01
    - To Department of the Army [from Jeanmarie], 1981-08-05
    - Margaret Puckette, 1981-11-05
    - Walter Underwood, 1981-12-02
    - Margaret Puckette [Attached article], 1981-12-02
    - Grungy?, 1982-02-15
    - To Walter Underwood [from Jeanmarie], 1982-03-04
    - Baya, 1982-03-05
    - Walter Underwood, 1982-03-21
    - Matthew Amend, 1982-03-22
    - Dawn Nabatoff, 1982-04-14
    - Jon Marmor, 1982-04-22
    - Walter Underwood [Attached Article], 1982-05-06
    - Garland Irwin [Re: Susan Leigh Franklin], 1982-05-18
    - J. Stahl, 1982-05-26
    - Walter Underwood, 1982-05-28
    - Jon Marmor, 1982-05-29
    - Charlotte Amend, 1982-06-25
    - Mount Carmel High School, 1982-06-30
    - The Women's Lifetime Development Center, 1982-07-02
    - P.M.A. [Jeanmarie's father], 1982-07-17
    - Margie Maguire, 1982-06-21
    - Jon Marmor, 1982-07-21
    - Susan, n.d.
    - Aunt Jan, n.d.
    - Grandma, n.d.
  - Sub-Series B: Documents
    - Photographs (8), ca. early 1980s (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Newsclippings, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Life Reflections, 1977, 1978, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Sub-Series C: Notebooks
    - January - July 1981 Notebook, 1981-01-1981-07 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - May - August 1981 Notebook, 1981-05-1981-08 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - October 1981- January 1982 Journal, 1981-10-1982-01 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1982 Journal (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series II: School Notes and Papers
  - Sub-Series A: Books
    - The Art of Making Sense: A Guide to Logical Thinking by Lionel Ruby (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Barron's How to Prepare for the Graduate Record Examination by Brownstein and Weiner (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - The Letters of Paul: Conversations in Context by Calvin J. Roetzel (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Life Studies For the Union Dead by Robert Lowell (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - "Martinhouse" Poetry Book (2), Spring, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Scripts People Live: Transactional Analysis of Life Scripts by Claude M. Steiner (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Self-Portrait in a Convex Mirror: Poems by John Ashbery (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Sub-Series B: Rice Documents
    - Rice Student Directory, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Rice Course Schedule & Financial Aid Note, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Rice University 69th Commencement Program & Invitation, 1982-05-08 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - School Essays and Exams, 1977-1982 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Sub-Series C: Class Notes
    - English 375a with Dr. Grob, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - English 340 with Edward Snow, Spring 1982 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - English 412 with Professor Wood, Spring 1982 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - French 110, Spring 1982 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Medical Ethics with Ruth Mattern, Spring 1982 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Series III: Post-graduation Research
  - Resume, 1982-06-27 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Houston Maps, ca. early 1980s (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Advanced Education Information, ca. early 1980s (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Homeless Children & Food Bank Research, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Public Affairs Writer Job Search Research, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Teaching Abroad Research, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Series IV: Memorabilia
  - Dress Patterns (2), ca. early 1980s (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - 2 Hand-carved floral decorative wooden boxes (Box 4)
  - Hexagonal metal box (Box 4)
  - Miniature sewing kit (containing red, green, and black thread wrapped around a wood chip, a small retractable knife, tweezers, a needle case with 5 needles, and a button-hole-opener) (Box 4)